A Guide to the Gregory Family Papers, 1764-1857
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Gregory Family Papers, 1764-1857
Library of Virginia
25325, 25326, 25327
.87 cubic feet (2 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 25325 gift of Roger Gregory, Jr., through Elizabeth Coalter, 1 May 1961.
Accession 25326 photostats made from originials in-house, Library of Virginia, 1 May 1961.
Accession 25327 photostats made from originals in-house, Library of Virginia, 1 May 1961.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Gregory family was prominent in early Virginia history, dating back to the 1620s. "Elsing Green", in King William County, was the home of the Gregory's for more than a century, until 1935. Richard Gregory, a justice in King and Queen County, was the father of Roger and Richard. Roger (ca. 1690-1732) married Mildred Washington, daughter of Lawrence Washington, and deeded the Mount Vernon estate to Augustine Washington, George Washington's father. Richard married a Miss West and they had several children including Roger (b. 1729) married to Mary Cole Claiborne (d. 1771) and Fanny Lowry.
William Gregory (1767-1840), son of Roger (b. 1729) was married to Anne Sutherland. He served in the Virginia House of Delegates, 1798-1807, and 1815-1816. His son, Roger (1795-1850), married Maria Ellett, and they had three sons: Junius C. and Deucalion, who became doctors, and Roger (b. 1833). Roger was married to Elizabeth Frances Allen, daughter of William C. Allen and Alleville Slaughter. He served as a Liuetenant Colonel in the 87th Regiment Virginia Militia, was a judge of the County Court, member of the House of Delegates 1879-1880, represented King William and Hanover Counties at the Constitutional Convention of 1901- 1902, and was professor of law at Richmond College (now University of Richmond).
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1764-1857, of the Gregory family of King William County, Virginia, as well as the related families of Garrett, Roane, and Turner. The papers reflect the personal and business affairs of the Gregory family, especially Nathaniel (b. 1765), Roger (1795-1850), William (1767-1840), and Evelina Gregory Garrett Brooks. The collection includes the estate papers of William Gregory (1767-1840) and Robert Lumpkin Garrett, husband of Evelina (Gregory) Garrett. These papers include deeds, correspondence, accounts, and receipts for the sale of slaves. Also included are papers relating to the guardianship of Junius Gregory by trustee Maria Gregory, Mary Turner by trustee William Gregory and Junius B. Roane by trustee Roger Gregory. These materials include receipts for clothes and books purchased in Richmond, Virginia, as well as doctor and tuition bills.
The correspondence, dated 1790-1845, is mainly between William and Roger Gregory relating to legal and business matters in King and Queen, and King William Counties. Of note are the deeds for land in Campbell, King and Queen, and King William Counties, Virginia, dating from 1764-1843. Some of the deeds for land in King William County are accompanied by surveys.
The collection also contains numerous accounts, promissory notes, and receipts relating to the business and personal expenses of the Gregory family. Included are business accounts for cargo shipped aboard or sold from the ship Mary and schooner Whig. Also included are accounts for personal items such as food, shoes, funerals, and mourning clothes.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Contents List
- Accounts, 1803-1855 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1790-1845 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 2)
- Deeds, 1764-1843 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 3)
- Estate accounts, 1842-1852 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 4)
- Garrett, Robert Lumpkin (Estate) 1823-1851 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 5)
- Gregory, Junius C., 1852-1857 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 6)
- Gregory, William (Estate), 1840-1848 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 7)
- Legal materials, 1815-1849 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 8)
- Promissory notes, 1796-1848 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 9)
- Receipts, 1802-1853 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 10)
- Roane, Junius 1837-1851 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 11)
- Turner, Mary, 1826-1841 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 12)
- Wills, 1776-1827 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 13)
- Clippings, 1804-1852 (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 1)
- Deeds, 1772-1831 (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 2)